Finding aid to the Victoria Schrager, Papers CA.MS.00348
Smith College Archives
Victoria Schrager Papers
1919-1944
Smith College Archives
Schrager, Victoria, 1919-1943
CA.MS.00348
0.833 linear feet (2 containers)
Professor of English. Contains photographs, letters, clippings, and published academic work.
Biographical / Historical
Victoria Schrager was born in Chicago, Illinois on May 2, 1919. Her parents were Dr. Victor L. Schrager and Jean Brawner Schrager. She had one brother, a twin, who served in the military during World War II. A member of the Class of 1940, she attended Smith College, where she was elected to Phi Beta Kappa her junior year, and won the Sophia Smith Scholarship. Schrager was involved in the theater department as an actress and playwright. She wrote "How Like a God" in 1939 commemorating President Neilson's retirement that year. She was also her junior year's class president, and was the head of the student government her senior year. Schrager graduated from the college with the highest honors in English. During the years of 1941-1942 she worked as a research assistant at Harvard University helping to prepare the book Shakespeare and the Nature of Man by Theodore Spenser. After Smith she worked as the Student Refugee Secretary at the International Student Senate in New York City, then received her Masters at Radcliffe in 1942. She returned to Smith as an English professor for 1942-1943, and was also the editor of the Smith Alumnae Quarterly. Her untimely death on October 24, 1943, shocked Smith College, where she was a beloved professor and colleague.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists mostly of Victoria Schrager's early academic essays, and published scholarly work. It also includes drafts, first manuscripts, and unfinished footnotes. The biographical material was mostly produced in the wake of her death, and contains a statement from President Herbert Davis.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Victoria Schrager papers were donated to the Smith College Archives from a number of sources.
Schrager, Victoria, 1919-1943
- General, 1936-1943 (Box 1011.2, Folder 1)
- Clippings re: death, 1943 (Box 1011.2, Folder 2)
- Victoria Schrager Memorial Fund: Letters, 1944 (Box 1011.2, Folder 3)
- Victoria Schrager Memorial Fund: Donors (2 folders), 1943-1944 (Box 1011.2, Folder 4-5)
- Victoria Schrager Memorial Fund: Donors by College Houses, 1937-1938 (Box 1011.2, Folder 6)
- Victoria Schrager Memorial Fund: Memorial Room, 1943 (Box 1011.2, Folder 7)
- Photographs, 1940-1943 (Box 1011.2, Folder 8)
- Class notes: Latin 25, 1937-1938 (Box 1011.2, Folder 9-10)
- Loisell lectures on Shakespeare by Theodore Spencer, 1941 (Box 1011.2, Folder 11)
- Teaching notes and lectures, undated (Box 1011.2, Folder 12)
- Academic notebooks: English, Chemistry, 1930-1931 (Box 1011.2, Folder 13)
- Notes from Ruskin's "Lectures on Art", undated (Box 1011.2, Folder 14)
- School papers: "The Art Itself is Nature" (Honors Thesis), 1940 (Box 1012, Folder 1)
- School papers: "The Comedy of Pygmalion and Galatea: George Meredith studied in Diana of Crossways", 1939 (Box 1012, Folder 2)
- School papers: "Conversation at Midnight", 1942 (Box 1012, Folder 3)
- School papers: "Deus Perfectus et Summa Bonatate Plenus: Notes toward a Commentary on a Phase of the Sententiae", 1942 (Box 1012, Folder 4)
- School papers: "The Fourth Age of Poetry: A Study of Thomas Love Peacock", 1940 (Box 1012, Folder 5)
- School papers: "This Enmity is Found in England: Adam and Satan in Paradise Lost", 1941 (Box 1012, Folder 6)
- School papers: "King, Father, Royal Dane: A Study of the Ghost in Hamlet", 1942 (Box 1012, Folder 7)
- Professional work: "For the Duration Dialogue on the Values of Art", 1941 (Box 1012, Folder 8-9)
- Lecture: "Dramas of Limbo", 1942 (Box 1012, Folder 10)
- Lecture: "Johnson versus the Honeysuckle Life", undated (Box 1012, Folder 11)
- Lecture: "A Mechanic Part of Wit", 1942 (Box 1012, Folder 12)
- "Autumn Quarter", undated (Box 1012, Folder 13)
- "The Double Man", undated (Box 1012, Folder 14)
- "Federal Theatre" play script, undated (Box 1012, Folder 15)
- "If Ye Break Faith" by Victoria Schrager and Casey Geddes Miller, undated (Box 1012, Folder 16)
- "Influence of Psychologies on American Drama", undated (Box 1012, Folder 17)
- Listen in a Kindly Spirit: Recent and Contemporary Footnotes on the Aesthetic Theories of Plato and Aristotle (unfinished), undated (Box 1012, Folder 18-19)